A Guide to the Papers of John McLaren McBryde, 1900-1907
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- The Times-Urquhart. (Box-folder 3:87)
  - a: Notable letterhead from David Bradley Manufacturing Co., 1902.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Wings Ellet & Crump Shoe Co., 1901.
- Vaiden-Veitor. (Box-folder 3:88)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Valentine's Meat-Juice Co., 1901.
  - b: Formal resignation form from Vaughn, a student in poor health.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Southside Foundry & Machine Works, 1903.
  - d: Letters from the Imperial German Cosul in Richmond, E.K. Veitor, 1904.
- Untitled--Correspondence with companies concerning material for uniforms. (Box-folder 3:89)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Voghts, Quast and Company importers, 1901.
  - b: Sample of gray padding from Voghts, Quast and Company.
  - c: Four gray padding samples and one white sample from Voghts, Quast and Company.
  - d: Four samples of blue uniform wool from Uhlig and Company Woolens, 1902.
- Waddell-Ware. (Box-folder 3:90)
  - a: Notable letterhead of Everett Waddey Co., 1900-1902.
  - b: Letter including a written statement from student concerning a problem with the class of 1905, including a letter backing up the student, April 15, 1903.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Wallerstien Produce Co., 1902.
  - d: Notable letterhead from the Wall Street Journal about a subscription, 1902.
- Originals from folder 90 Waddell-Ware. (Box-folder 3:91)
- Ware-White. (Box-folder 3:92)
  - a: Notable letterhead from A. A. Waterman & Co. for the Lincoln Pen.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Watson & Newell Co. Silver smiths, 1903.
  - c: Letter from the Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Agriculture, 1902 concerning the Quarantine laws.
  - d: Notable letterhead from F. Weber & Co., 1904.
  - e: Notable letterhead form Fred Van Orman & Co., 1900.
  - f: Notable letterhead from James T. White & Co. Publishers, 1903.
- White-Wiers. (Box-folder 3:93)
  - a: Notable letterhead from the Knoxville Sentinel, 1904.
  - b: Notable letterhead from W. J. Whitehurst, 1902.
- Wilkins-Willis. (Box-folder 3:94)
  - a: Notable letterhead from J. A. Wilkins Co. Printers, 1900.
  - b: Letter from the Grand-Camp of Confederate Veterans of Virginia wanting to secure the V.P.I. Cadet Band, 1902.
  - c: Letter with added paper concerning the credentials for the entrance examination for matriculants at Baltimore Medical College.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Williams Bros. Inc., 1901.
- Willis-Withrow. (Box-folder 3:95)
  - a: Official notice from the Registrar's Office concerning failures and missing course work, 1904.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Central Warehouse leaf tobacco.
  - c: 5 Advertisements with photo and description of desks from Everett Waddey Co.
  - d: Letter from W.E.Wine accepting the position of assistant in drawing, 1904.
- Originals from 95: Willis-Withrow. (Box-folder 3:96)
- Withrow-Wyson. (Box-folder 4:97)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Pan-American Exposition 1901, Buffalo N.Y. U.S.A.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the State of Georgia Senate Chamber 1904, from W.A. Warsham, concerning a position in Chemistry.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Eskew, Smith & Cannon Manufacturing Confectioners, 1904.
  - d: Notable letterhead from E.A. Wright, 1903.
- Yager-Zallikoffer. (Box-folder 4:99)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Corinth Lumber Company, 1901.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Mount Airy Furniture Company, 1903.
- Applications for employment by students, 1900-1901. (Box-folder 4:100)
  - a: Series of Formal applications for employment from the students, 1901.
- Adair-Kent Problems, 1902-1903. (Box-folder 4:101)
  - a: Testimonies on the Childrey & Matthews Case, with recommendations for Matthews punishment.
  - b: Notable letterhead from N.R. Bowman and Company, leaf tobacco, 1902.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Common Council City of Lynchburg, 1903.
  - d: Letter in regard to the handling of hazing at V.P.I. from a Rector of St. Stephens Church, Randolph Royall Clairborne.
  - e: Pamphlet from University of Wisconsin, " A Circular of Information relating to the Short Course in Agriculture at the University of Wisconsin 1902-1903."
  - f: Report form the Presidents office concerning three cadets for: "Seriously and Disrespectfully interfering with the Officer of the Day in the discharge of his duty on the Night of April 28th."
  - g: Report of the students work for term ending January 3, 1903 with a letter from the parents.
  - h: Notable letterhead from Wm. N. Grubb Insurance, 1903.
  - i: Committee report from the committee appointed by the class of 1904 concerning the Brandenburg Case.
  - j: Notable letterhead from the "Oakly" Nelson County Virginia, Buffalo Station P.O., 1902.
  - k: Notable letterhead from U.S. Navy Yard Norfolk, VA, 1903.
  - l: Notable letterhead from Cranes Nest Coal & Coke Co., 1902.
- Ligon-Wade, McBryde Problems, 1902-1903. (Box-folder 4:102)
  - a: Letter from a father to the school concerning problems with his son and a misappropriated check.
  - b: Review in the Bristol Cavalier, February 14, 1903 of V.P.I. band.
  - c: Notable letterhead from John E.Rose & Co., 1903.
  - d: Statement signed by committee from class, 1904.
  - e: Evaluation of Mess Hall food, 1904.
- Addison-Amey, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:103)
  - a: Letters regarding problems with an auditor refusing payment of accounts made against Crop Pest Commission Funds.
- Bason-Butt, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:104)
  - a: Notable letterhead from American Trust & Savings Bank.
  - b: Letter from an ex-student who was just named as County Health Officer of Montgomery County.
  - c: Notable letterhead from J.P. Bell Company, 1905.
  - d: One of the letters referred to in the book titled The First One Hundred Years, McBryde's chapter in the Quotes at the end of the chapter. The quote concerning sending a worm to be identified, 1905.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Bishop Furniture Co. 1905. Concerning the recent fire at Science Hall.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Virginia Bridge & Iron Co., 1905.
  - g: Letter accompanied by a newspaper article titled "Crush Rowdyism Say Educators."
  - h: Notable letterhead from the Teacher's Co-Operative Association, 1905.
  - i: Report of vacancy form from the Teacher's Co-Operative Association.
- Calvert-Cunningham, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:105)
  - a: Various letters of interest concerning an opening position in the Department of Chemistry at Virginia Tech.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the Bugle, V.P.I., 1906.
  - c: A request for more information regarding V.P.I. from the Chicago Tribune, 1905, due to more requests for information to the newspaper.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Commercial Envelope and Box Company, 1905.
  - e: Notable letterhead from W. S. Copeland of the Times Dispatch regarding a student's record, Richmond Virginia, 1905.
  - f: Telegram from the Western Union Telegraph Company Inc., 1905 with conditions and company terms on the back of the telegram.
- Darnall-Finch (includes Fire), 1905. (Box-folder 4:106)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Co., 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Eugene Deitzgen Co., 1905.
  - c: Cover letter for job as Assistant Professor in Chemistry for 1906, from Mr. Oskar Eikstein, 1905.
  - d: Letter concerning the Southern Educational Conference April 26-28, Letter from J. Wm. Flinn, South Carolina College.
  - e: Blank advertising contract for Official Southern States School Guide, 1905, Forman Co., Publishers.
  - f: Various letters concerning the fire at Science Hall.
- Grandy-Guigon, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:107)
  - a: Letter from A.B. Guigon Attorney at Law, 1905 concerning the junior class incident, the Tinsley case.
  - b: Enclosed correspondence between Col. Johnson and A.B. Guigon in reference to Guigon's sons record, 1905.
- Hall-Huffard, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:108)
  - a: Notable letterhead from J. Bumgardner Distilling Company, 1905.
  - b: Inquiry of the opening position in the Department of Chemistry.
  - c: Brochure for a building, sent to V.P.I. after the destruction of Science Hall. Advertisement reads "College, Sanitarium, Asylum or School Property for sale or lease."
  - d: Letter from the General Assembly of Georgia concerning two questions regarding expenditures and present values, 1905.
  - e: Schedule of lectures, Etc., 1905-1906, formal document.
- Isaac-Luke, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:109)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Lane Brothers Company Contractors, with map on the back, 1905.
- Mabee-Murrill, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:110)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Designers Engravers Printers Consolidated, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The N.E. Spessard Co., general department store, 1905.
  - c: Letter from a detective agency with regard to fires with newspaper articles, business card and references.
  - d: Letter from The School and College Bureau, Chicago, 1905. Claiming to have a select list of members, requesting that V.P.I. send their list of openings to them for advertisement.
  - e: Letter from a parent including actual cut out sections of the Course Catalogue.
  - f: Notable letterhead from The University College of Medicine, 1905.
  - g: A series of letters from W.G. Melvin, concerning the Junior class incident and the actions taken against the boys.
  - h: Notable letterhead from the American Saving Stamp Co., 1905.
  - i: Advertisement for the Northern Neck News, Warsaw, Virginia, the newspaper for Richmond, Lancaster, Westmoreland and Northcumberland counties, 1905.
  - j: Notable letterhead from The United States Envelope Company, 1905.
  - k: Letter from W.A. Murrill concerning a lecture he is giving at Tech titled "Cuba and Cuban farming," 1905.
- Nightingale-Powell, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:111)
  - a: Notable letterhead from The Parker Pen Company.
  - b: Letter noting problems with the shop report and budget.
  - c: Letter form Virginia Anthracite Coal and Railway Co. concerning the problems with their service to V.P.I. and the winter weather, 1905.
- Ramey-Russell, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:112)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Hackney Wagon Company Manufacturers, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Republican Publishing Company, 1905.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Buena Vista Plaster and Mining Company, 1905.
  - d: Letter from Robertson & Wingfield Attourneys at Law concerning an incident taking place two years prior to the letter and requesting information relating to the case, 1905.
  - e: Notable letterhead from H.W. Rountree & Brother Trunk and Bag Co, 1905.
- Saul-Sycle, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:113)
  - a: Letter including article from the newspaper on an examination for Civil Engineers.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Public Ledger with map on the back, 1905.
  - c: Notable letterhead from The Smith Premier Typewriter Co., 1905.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Ohio State University 1905, wanted a complete set of financial reports of the Land-Grant colleges, established under the act of July 2nd 1862.
- Talcott-Villafranca, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:114)
  - a: Letter from T.M.R. Talcott to president McBryde in reference to the article in the Times-Dispatch which discusses the terms under which the Junior class students will be reinstated. An argument over the punishment, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Taylor Bros., 1905.
  - c: Letter from R.H. Tebbs in reference to the insubordination of the Junior class "The Coulter Affair."
  - d: Letter from the Southern Intelligence Office, 1905, containing a cut out advertisement for V.P.I.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Underwood & Underwood stereoscopic photographs, 1905 concerning summer employment of 1500 students.
- Winston-Zimmerman, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:115)
  - a: Letter from S.P. Withers in regard to the Junior class trouble,` 1905.
- Adamson-Audel, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:116)
  - a: Outgoing letter to A.L. Adamson in regard to his son, 1904.
  - b: Outgoing letter to J.A. Albert concerning some incident of a student leaving campus and being charged with outrageous conduct. Student supported by Dr. McBryde.
  - c: Notable letterhead from The Charlotte Trouser Co., 1905.
  - d: Letter to McBryde from Mrs S.H. Anderson about her son's dissatisfaction with V.P.I. accompanied by a sympathetic response form McBryde, 1904.
- Baker-Burroughs, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:117)
  - a: Letter of apology from a student member of the Junior class for his behavior in the Coulter Affair and asking to be reinstated.
  - b: Miscellaneous correspondence from the Dean of Faculty. Many letters referring to the disciplinary action taken by the faculty in the Coulter Affair.
- Caldwell-Cunningham, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:118)
  - a: Miscellaneous correspondence regarding the reinstatement of various students from the Junior class that resigned.
- Dalton-Dyer, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:119)
  - a: Miscellaneous correspondence from parents with replies from the Dean of Faculty, referring to: Catalogue requests, Coulter Affair and reinstatement, student records and possible employment.
- Eastman-Frost, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:120)
  - a: Miscellaneous correspondence about: Financial difficulties, reinstatement of students involved in the Coulter Affair, Catalogue requests, A boy McBryde is to look after during his fathers absence on the U.S.S. Buffalo.
  - b: Letter from Flournoy, Sparklin Architechs regarding the recent fire and the need for a new building. Includes a drawn picture of a dormitory building at Washington and Lee University that was an example of their buildings.
  - c: A picture in The Baltimore News, 1905, of the plans for The Marlborough Apartment Hotel.
- Garborg-Guigon, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:121)
  - a: Notable letterhead from The Combination Rubbery Mfg. Co., 1904.
  - b: Miscellaneous correspondence referring to: The reinstatement of members of the Junior class, Requests for information referring to V.P.I., and student records.
- Hall-Hope, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:122)
  - a: Letter referring to the requirements for entrance into the freshman class, 1905.
  - b: Various correspondence referring to the reinstatement of students from the Junior class.
  - c: Letter from the University of Arkansas requesting a copy of the rules and regulations at V.P.I. for reference as they revise their set of rules and regulations and wish to compare them.
  - d: Letter from the Commercial Association, renewing their invitation to attend the "Good Road" Meeting, 1905.
  - e: Advertisement for certificates, includes sample certificates with conditions and important changes of rates, rules and regulations on the back, 1904.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Tennessee Furniture and Supply Company, 1904.
- Hughes-Lunsford, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:123)
  - a: Various letters referring to the reinstatement of students of the Junior class, 1905.
  - b: Letter to the manager of the Virginia-Tennessee Telephone Company, Pulaski, complaining of the unsatisfactory phone service and the problems Tech is having with their service, 1905.
  - c: Notable letterhead from G.W. Litz Stock Company, 1905.
- McAdams-Mosher, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:124)
  - a: Notable letterhead from The Citizens Bank, 1905.
  - b: General Correspondence.
  - c: Letters regarding the reinstatement of members of the Junior class, 1905.
- Noland-Osterlch, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:125)
  - a: General Correspondence.
  - b: Letters concerning the reinstatement of members of the Junior class.
- Palmer-Russell, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:126)
  - a: Letter that references when the name of the college was changed from the Virginia Agricultural & Mechanical College to Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
  - b: Letters in reference to the reinstatement of members the Junior class, 1905.
  - c: Letter referring to the stance on Prohibition that the County holds with the exception of Radford.
  - d: Notable letterhead from the Hackney Wagon Company, 1905.
- Sanborn-Simmons, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:127)
  - a: Correspondence regarding the resignation of the Junior class and the reinstatement of the students. Including a letter that quotes the letter sent by the faculty stating what they expected to be addressed in the letter and what the real problem with this act of insubordination was.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Hotel Imperial, 1905.
- Somers-Vandegrift, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:128)
  - a: Letters in reference to the reinstatement of members of the Junior class, 1905.
  - b: Letter from the East Orange Gazzette, 1905, requesting information about Luther D. Martin and his association with V.P.I., includes a newspaper photograph of Luther Martin.
  - c: Letter from a student at Emory and Henry College requesting information about Graduate classes at V.P.I., 1905.
- Wade-Yeaton, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 4:129)
  - a: Letters in reference to the reinstatement of members of the Junior class, 1905.
  - b: Letter from McBryde explaining the conditions and guidelines the letter for reinstatement must follow, 1905.
- Abbitt-Cutshaw, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:130)
  - a: Notable letterhead from the Hotel Rennert, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the Southern Tobacconist and Modern Farmer, 1905.
  - c: Three letters from Atlantic and Birmingham Construction Co. 1906 asking for character references for students that applied for various jobs.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Brown & Bailey Co., 1906.
  - e: Letter from a parent concerned with the associations of his son and a concern of another student carrying a gun to school.
  - f: Letter from the Board of Trustees of the University of Chicago announcing the death of President William Rainey Harper, 1906.
  - g: Notable letterhead from The Cox Hat Company, 1906.
- Dammann-Funsten, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:131)
  - a: Notable letterhead from A.B. Dick Company, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Eimer & Amend, 1906.
  - c: Letter asking for reinstatement of a student that was previously expelled.
  - d: Letter from secretary of the Chamber of Commerce of Newport News in reference to supporting a bill.
- Gallalee-Jones, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:132)
  - a: Letter from Mr. Geckler, from affiliated schools, Georgia School of Technology, including a questionnaire regarding V.P.I.'s dealings with affiliated schools, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Stephen Putney Shoe Company, 1905.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Straton & Bragg Company, 1905.
  - d: Letter from the University of Georgia asking for information on The Men's Christian Association Building and the University relations with the Y.M.C.A.
  - e: Letter from Mr. Horsley in regards to the Christian Case.
  - f: Notable letterhead from M.H. Jennings & Son, 1905.
- Landis-Noland, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:133)
  - a: Letter from N.T. LaBaume A&I Agent for Norfolk and Western Railway on behalf of the president of N&W Railway, commending Blacksburg for its work and discussing the plans of the president visiting the school, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from James River Cement Works, 1905.
  - c: Letter from the United States Senate in reference to a bill introduced to the House of Representatives by Mr. Hull providing that certain colleges be placed on the list as depositories for government publications.
  - d: Invitation from the Trustees and the Faculty of the Maryland Agricultural College for the Semi-Centennial Celebration, March 6, 1906 in College Park, Maryland.
  - e: Notable letterhead from the president's office at Clemson College, 1905 concerning some bills pending before the General Assembly of South Carolina.
  - f: Invitation from Mercer University for the installment of Charles Lee Smith Phd as the president of the University in Macon Georgia, November 24, 1905.
  - g: Announcement of the Inauguration of Dr. Charles Lee Smith as the president of Mercer University in Macon Georgia, November 24, 1905, includes the program of events.
- Palmer-Tuok, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:134)
  - a: Two letters in Spanish from Francisco Planas, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Welch Lumber Company, 1905.
  - c: Notable letterhead from The Park Hotel, 1905.
  - d: Notable letterhead from The Charleston Hotel Co., 1906.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Shenandoah County Building and Loan Association, 1906.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Straus Gunst & Co., 1906.
- Dee-Zepp, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:135)
  - a: Notable letterhead from the Underwood Typewriter Co.
- Albarez-Keeler, Campbell incoming-outgoing, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:136)
  - a: Letter from the War Department Office of the Chief Engineers about adding V.P.I. on a list in order to follow the regulations in promoting former students to Junior Engineers, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the Bugle, 1906.
  - c: Notable letterhead from The Caxton Co., 1906.
  - d: Letter to Mr. Dobbins giving permission to have a stand on campus during Commencement, and the conditions under which this was to be permitted.
  - e: Letter concerning sending an Education Commission to China, 1906.
  - f: Letter to John Goode discussing McBryde's illness and the proceedings at graduation, 1906.
  - g: Letter from the Beta Theta Pi's looking for information of an old brother of the fraternity, 1906.
  - h: Memorandum concerning the sending of An Educational Commission to China, Edmund J.James, President of the University of Illinois.
- Larsen-Wood, Campbell Incoming-Outgoing, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 4:137)
  - a: Letter from the Methodist concerning the V.P.I. advertisement, includes the actual newspaper cutout of the advertisement published, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Decatur Chamber of Commerce, with various pictures of Illinois on the back of the letterhead, 1906.
  - c: Notable letterhead form Southwest Virginia Enterprise, 1906.
- Requisition Orders, January-June 1905. (Box-folder 4:138)
  - a: Requisition orders of the Field Experiments, 1904.
  - b: Request for Bath tub and Hand Basin for Prof. Vorter's house, 1904.
  - c: Requisition orders of the Department of Uniforms, 1904.
  - d: Requisition orders of the Department of Virginia Crop Pest Commission, 1904.
  - e: Requisition orders of the Department of Equipment, 1904.
  - f: Requisition orders of the Department of Mechanical Engineering, 1904.
  - g: Requisition orders of the Department of Farm Supplies, 1905.
  - h: Requisition orders of the Department of Garden and Factory, 1905.
  - i: Requisition orders of the Department of Books, 1905.
  - j: Requisition orders of the Department of Military, 1905.
  - k: Requisition orders of the Department of Agriculture, 1905.
  - l: Requisition orders of the Department of Laundry, 1905.
  - m: Requisition orders of the Department of College, 1905.
  - n: Requisition orders of the Department of General Chemistry, 1905.
  - o: Requisition orders of the Department of English, 1905.
  - p: Requisition orders of the Department of Shops, 1905.
- Requisition Orders, 1907-1908. (Box-folder 4:139)
  - a: Requisition order of the Department of Rhetoric, 1907.
  - b: Requisition orders of the Department of Repairs, 1907.
  - c: Requisition order of the Department of Farms, 1907.
  - d: Requisition orders of the Department of Shops, 1908.
  - e: Requisition orders of the Department of Mess, 1907.
  - f: Requisition orders of the Department of Garden & Factory, 1908.
  - g: Requisition orders of the Department of Military, 1908.
  - h: Requisition orders of the Department of Uniforms, 1908.
  - i: Requisition orders of the Department of Physics, 1907.
  - j: Requisition orders of the Department of Office Supplies, 1907.
  - k: Requisition orders of the Department of Graphics, 1907.
  - l: Requisition orders of the Department of Postage and Stationery, 1907.